Preliminary Guide to the William Henry Bishop Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
William Henry Bishop papers
1800-1930
MS 83
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
13.75
(29 boxes, 1 folio)
Author, diplomat. Diaries, consular papers documenting his service in Italy and miscellaneous personal papers including correspondence with William Dean Howells and Armando Palacio Valdés, notebooks, genealogical materials, subjects files on Maria Bashkirtseff and a few papers of his son, Julian B. Bishop, who died in 1912. William Henry Bishop's diaries, which make up half the collection, are in 127 volumes spanning the years of 1874-1928 and reflect his extensive travels in the United States and Italy. His consular papers contain correspondence, notes, clippings and photographs on political and social conditions in Italy (1903-1910) with material relating to the self-styled Duca di Santa Elisabetta, 1904-1910; the Petrosino murder case, 1904-1912; public security in Sicily, 1907; the Messina earthquakes, 1906-1908; consular relations between Panama and Palermo, 1905; material on immigration from Sicily; and material on the Taraca Expedition in the Philippines. The 2012-M-035 addition to the William Henry Bishop papers include consular material, correspondence, draft manuscripts and notes from 1841 to 1930.
Bishop, William Henry, 1847-1928
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the estate of William H. Bishop, 1929; transfer from Beinecke Rare Book Library, 2011.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series and one addition: I. Consular Papers. II. Personal Papers. III. Diaries.
Scope and Contents
The papers of William Henry Bishop have been sorted by type and subject, but are otherwise unprocessed. They have been divided into three series: Consular Papers, Personal Papers, and Diaries.
Series I contains correspondence and other documents pertaining primarily to Bishop's consulates at Genoa and Palermo, Italy, between 1903 and 1910. Aside from regular consulate business, topics discussed include the self-styled Duca di Santa Elisabetta, the Petrosino murder case, public security in Sicily, the Messina earthquake, consular relations between Palermo and Panama, immigration from Sicily, and the Taraca Expedition in the Philippines. There is also a small amount of historical material from the consulates pre-dating Bishop's appointment.
Series II contains personal correspondence with William Dean Howells, Armando Palacio Valdés, and others. Subject files, which are made up of correspondence, writings, notes, and printed matter, cover such topics as Marie Bashkirtseff, sundials, and Bishop family genealogy. There is also a small amount of printed matter pertaining to the Yale College class of 1867, and some papers relating to Julian B. Bishop, son of William Henry Bishop. An assortment of memorabilia includes passports, diplomas, and certificates bearing the signatures of Vittorio Emanuele III, Hamilton Fish, Theodore Roosevelt, and William H. Seward, among others.
Series III contains Bishop's diaries for the years 1874 through 1927, kept in 127 small volumes and notebooks. There are also a few notes written by Bishop about the diaries.
The 2012-M-035 addition to the William Henry Bishop papers include consular material, correspondence, draft manuscripts and notes from 1841 to 1930.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
William Henry Bishop, B.A. 1867.
Born January 7, 1847, in Hartford, Conn.
Died September 26, 1928, in Brooklyn, Conn.
Father, Elias Bishop; son of John and Harriet (Heminway) Bishop; descendant of Governor James Bishop of the New Haven Colony, and of John Bishop, a founder of Guilford, Conn., in 1639; descendant also of Major Moses Mansfield, who married Abigail, sister of Elihu Yale. Mother, Catherine (Kelley) Bishop. Yale relatives include the Rev. Jacob Heminway (B.A. 1704) (great-great-great-uncle), the first and for some months the only student of Yale College.
Hartford Public High School and preparatory department of St. John's College, Fordham, N. Y. Entered Yale as a Sophomore in 1864; prize for English poem in Sophomore year; Class poet; an editor of Yale Courant; member of Yale Crew, Linonia (president), Kappa Sigma Epsilon, Delta Beta Xi, and Delta Kappa Epsilon; graduate member of Wolf's Head.
Studied architecture in office of Peter B. Wight, in New York City; art critic on New York Evening Post; draftsman in office of Government architect in Washington; editor and proprietor of Milwaukee Journal of Commerce (with his classmate, Henry A. Chittenden) 1873-1875, and of Milwaukee Daily Commercial Times 1875-1877; subsequently traveled in Mexico and abroad; lived in France 1888-1893; instructor in French and Spanish at Yale 1893-1903; American consul at Genoa, Italy, 1903-1904, and at Palermo, Italy, 1905-1910, when he resigned; awarded medal of honor by King of Italy, for services in aiding sufferers during the Messina earthquake in 1908; since 1910 had lived in the United States, and of late years in Brooklyn, Conn., and devoted his time largely to painting; exhibited at the New Haven Paint and Clay Club in 1924; had also exhibited sketches at the Academy of Design in New York City in 1872, and in 1874 sketched Milwaukee for Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper; author: Detmold (1879), The House of a Merchant Prince (1882), Choy Susan and Other Stories (1884), Old Mexico and Her Lost Provinces (1884), Fish and Men in the Maine Islands (1885), The Golden Justice (1887), A House Hunter in Europe (1893), Sergeant Von (anonymously) (1889), The Faience Violin (translated from the French of Champfleury) (1893), A Pound of Cure (1894), Writing to Rosina (1894), The Brown Stone Boy and Other Queer People (reissued as Queer People ) (1902), The Yellow Snake (reissued as Tons of Treasure ) (1902) and Anti-Babel (1919); author also of a war song, "The Khaki and the Blue"; contributed short stories and articles to the Century, Harper's Magazine, Scribner's, Atlantic Monthly, and Nation; translated selections from Spanish authors for the Library of the World's Best Literature; commemorated the sixtieth reunion of his class in a poem; had been president of the Brooklyn Library Association, vice-president of the Connecticut Library Association, first vice-president of the Graduates Club, New Haven, and vice-president of Brooklyn Golf Club; honorary member of Connecticut chapter of American Institute of Architects; member of National Institute of Arts and Letters; Society of Letters, Science, and Arts, of Nice, France; Authors' Club, and Society of Colonial Wars.
Married July 28, 1886, in New York City, Mary Dearborn; daughter of George Follansbee Jackson (B.A. Bowdoin 1850, M.D. Jefferson Medical College 1853), and Rachel (Dearborn) Jackson. Children: Duquesnes (died in childhood), and Julian Brocklehurst (died in 1912 when a midshipman at United States Naval Academy). Mr. and Mrs. Bishop separated in 1917.
Death due to arteriosclerosis. Buried in the Old Cemetery at East Haven, Conn. By the terms of his will the residue of his estate was bequeathed to Yale, to establish the William Henry Bishop Fund for promoting the study of architecture in the University. He had also established in 1912 the Midshipman Julian B. Bishop Memorial, a fund of $1,000 to be used for the purchase and care of books on marine lore in the University Library.
From the Yale College Obituary Record, 1928.
Architecture; Art; Authors, American; Asia; Europe -- Description and travel; Europe; Italy -- Politics and government -- 20th Century; Italy -- Social conditions; Earthquakes -- Italy -- Messina; Philippines -- History; United States -- Foreign relations; Diaries; Authors; Diplomats; Bashikirtseva, Mariia Konstantinovna, 1860-1884; Bishop, Julian Brockelhurst, d. 1912; Bishop, William Henry, 1847-1928; Howells, William Dean, 1837-1920; Palacio Valdés, Armando, 1853-1938; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University -- Students
- Consular Papers, 1800-1912; Series I
  - Consular correspondence, 1904-1911 (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
  - Indices to consular letters; notes and copies of letters, 1904-1909 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters to WBH proposing an exchange of consulates, 1903-1909 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, notes and receipts re: consular administration at Palermo, 1904-1910 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Consular miscellany: correspondence and notes, 1902-1904 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Consular miscellany, [1902-1910] (Box 2, Folder 10-13)
  - Miscellaneous notes and papers, [1904-1909], undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Messina earthquake
    - Correspondence, notes, printed matter, 1908-1909 (Box 3, Folder 15-16)
    - Photographs and postcards, 1908 December (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - National Geographic and American Red Cross Bulletin articles, 1909 April (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1908-1909 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Newspaper clippings re: disasters, 1906-1909 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Petrosino murder
    - Correspondence, notes and newspaper clippings, 1909-1912 (Box 4, Folder 21-22)
    - Newspaper clippings and Black Hand article, 1907-1912 (Box 4, Folder 23-24)
  - Moving the remains of James Smithson, founder of the Smithsonian Institute to Washington, D.C.: Correspondence, notes, and printed matter, 1903-1904 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Taraca Expedition, Philippines: correspondence, notes and printed matter, 1904 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Government of Panama: correspondence and notes, 1905 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Duca di Santa Elisabetta: correspondence notes and printed matter, 1906 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Inspection of emigrants and disinfection of their baggage: correspondence and notes, 1907 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Dorsey, Goerge A., "The Wide, Wide World," re: Sicilian emigration; with correspondence and newspaper clippings, 1907-1910 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Public security in Sicily: correspondence newspaper clippings and notes, 1908-1910 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Notebooks (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - "Consular Memoranda", Undated (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Exports, Undated (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Genoa consulate: notes, newspaper clippings and receipts, [1903-1904?] (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Palermo consulate: newspaper clippings, [1904-1910?] (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Historical correspondence and other papers, 1800, 1821-1882, undated (Box 6, Folder 34a)
- Personal Papers, 1862-1930; Series II
  - Correspondence
    - Authors Club; with printed matter, [1920-1927] (Box 7, Folder 35)
    - Howells, Mildred, 1921 (Box 7, Folder 36)
    - Howells, William Dean; with printed matter, 1874-1920, undated (Box 7, Folder 36)
    - National Academy of Arts and Letters; with printed matter, [1919-1925] (Box 7, Folder 37)
    - New Haven Paint and Clay Club; with printed matter, 1924 (Box 7, Folder 38)
    - Palacio Valdés, Armando, 1895-1914 (Box 7, Folder 39)
    - Society of Colonial Wars; with printed matter, 1898-1903 (Box 7, Folder 40)
    - Letters and newspaper clippings [from French and Spanish friends and students?], [l890s] (Box 7, Folder 41)
    - Personal correspondence and miscellany, 1881-1927, undated (Box 8, Folder 42-43)
    - Correspondence re: writings, 1898-1926 (Box 8, Folder 44)
  - Subject Files
    - Bashkirtseff, Marie
      - Correspondence, photographs and printed matter, 1893-1920 (Box 8, Folder 45)
      - Notebook: "Intimate memoranda from her unpublished manuscript"; enclosing correspondence and printed matter, [1890s] (Box 8, Folder 46)
      - "The Homes of Marie Bashkirtseff at Nice," by W.H.B., Undated (Box 8, Folder 47)
      - Journal de Marie Bashkirtseff, Tome 1, 1890 (Box 8, Folder 48)
    - Sundials
      - Letters re: placement of a sundial on the Wright memorial, 1912-1913 (Box 8, Folder 49)
      - Notes, [1912-1913] (Box 9, Folder 50)
      - Printed matter, 1875-1918, undated (Box 9, Folder 51)
    - "Khaki and the Blue": manuscript of words & music, 1918 (Box 9, Folder 51a)
    - Genealogy
      - Correspondence, notes and photographs, [1894-1924], undated (Box 9, Folder 52-53)
      - Printed matter, Undated (Box 9, Folder 54)
      - "The Current Interest in Genealogy," lecture by WHB delivered at Sheffield Scientific School, 1896 (Box 10, Folder 55)
      - "Hunting an Ancestor in England," lecture by WHB delivered before the New Haven Historical Society, Undated (Box 10, Folder 56)
  - Writings and notes
    - "My Appendecitis [sic] Peril", 1901 (Box 10, Folder 57)
    - Notebook: "La Belle au Bois Dormant", Undated (Box 10, Folder 58)
    - Notebook: "Reviews and Notices of my Various Books", 1878-1898, undated (Box 10, Folder 59)
    - Notes re: rice industry investigation, Undated (Box 11, Folder 60)
    - Miscellaneous notes, Undated (Box 11, Folder 61)
  - Miscellany
    - Yale Class of 1867: printed matter and newspaper clippings, 1867, 1870 (Box 11, Folder 62)
    - Miscellaneous newspaper clippings, [1890s], undated (Box 11, Folder 63)
    - Printed matter, 1875-1930, undated (Box 11, Folder 64)
    - Correspondence and printed matter of Julian B. Bishop (son of WHB), 1910-1911 (Box 11, Folder 65)
    - Passport, certificates and other memorabilia, 1897-1913 (Box 11, Folder 66)
    - Diplomas/certificates, 1862-1920 (Box 23)
      General
      Oversize material.
- Diaries, 1874-1927, undated; Series III
  - Notes about diaries written by WHB, 1923 May 16 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Diaries
    - Europe, 1874 (Box 12, Folder 2-3)
    - Antwerp, Belgium, Paris, 1878 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Paris, Rouen, Northern Italy, 1878 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Northern Italy, Germany, London, 1878 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - London, Wales, Antwerp, 1878-1879 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - New York, 1878-1879 (Box 13, Folder 7a-10)
    - Saratoga, 1880 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Cuba, Mexico, 1881 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Mexico, 1881 (Box 13, Folder 15-18)
    - Narragansett, [1881?] (Box 13, Folder 19)
    - Council Bluffs, St. Louis, Virginia, 1881 (Box 13, Folder 20)
    - Kentucky, 1881 (Box 13, Folder 21)
    - New York, Newport, 1882-1883 (Box 13, Folder 22)
    - California, 1881 (Box 14, Folder 23-28)
    - Catskill, East Hampton, 1883-1884 (Box 14, Folder 29-30)
    - Washington, 1885 (Box 14, Folder 31)
    - The Highlands, 1885-1886 (Box 14, Folder 32-33)
    - New York to Cherbourg, 1888 (Box 15, Folder 34)
    - Cherbourg to Dinan, 1888 (Box 15, Folder 35)
    - Versailles, Paris, 1888 (Box 15, Folder 36)
    - Paris, 1889 (Box 15, Folder 37-38)
    - France, Algeria, Spain, 1889 (Box 15, Folder 39-40)
    - Paris, Nice, Villefranche, 1889-1890 (Box 15, Folder 41)
    - Nice, Paris, England, Avignon, Rome, Florence, 1890 (Box 15, Folder 42)
    - Florence, Venice, Nice, Alassio, 1890 (Box 16, Folder 43)
    - Verona, 1890 (Box 16, Folder 44)
    - Verona, Nice, 1890-1891 (Box 16, Folder 45)
    - Nice, Corsica, 1891 (Box 16, Folder 46)
    - Nice, 1891-1893 (Box 16, Folder 47-49)
    - New York, New Haven, 1893 (Box 16, Folder 50-52)
    - Vermont, Massachusetts, 1894 (Box 17, Folder 53)
    - New York to Liverpool, 1895 (Box 17, Folder 54)
    - Paris, France, Spain, 1895 (Box 17, Folder 55-56)
    - France, America, 1895 (Box 17, Folder 57)
    - New York to Le Havre, Paris, 1897 (Box 17, Folder 58)
    - Paris, Fontainbleau, Grenoble, Nice, Geneva, Chamonix, 1897 (Box 17, Folder 59-60)
    - Switzerland, Nancy, Sedan, Brussels, Waterloo, Holland, 1897 (Box 17, Folder 61)
    - Holland, Belgium, England, America, 1897 (Box 17, Folder 62)
    - New York to Gibraltar, Spain, 1902 (Box 17, Folder 63)
    - Spain, Naples, Genoa, Nice, 1902-1903 (Box 17, Folder 64-65)
    - Genoa, 1903 (Box 17, Folder 66-67)
    - Genoa, 1903-1904 (Box 18, Folder 68-71)
    - Elba, 1904 (Box 18, Folder 72)
    - Taormina, Palermo, 1905 (Box 18, Folder 73)
    - Palermo, New York, Washington, 1905 (Box 18, Folder 74-75)
    - Palermo, 1905-1907 (Box 18, Folder 76-82)
    - America, Canada, 1907 (Box 19, Folder 83)
    - America, Palermo, 1907-1908 (Box 19, Folder 84)
    - Palermo, 1908-1909 (Box 19, Folder 85-89)
    - Palermo, America, 1909-1910 (Box 19, Folder 90-91)
    - Palermo, 1910 (Box 19, Folder 92)
    - Brooklyn (Connecticut), 1910-1911 (Box 19, Folder 93-95)
    - Florida, 1911-1912 (Box 20, Folder 96-97)
    - Annapolis (Maryland), Brooklyn (Connecticut), 1912 (Box 20, Folder 98)
    - Maine, Chatauqua, Brooklyn (Connecticut), 1912-1913 (Box 20, Folder 99)
    - Bermuda, 1913 (Box 20, Folder 100)
    - Bermuda, New York, Connecticut, 1913 (Box 20, Folder 101)
    - Fairfield, Brooklyn (Connecticut), Nice, 1913-1914 (Box 20, Folder 102)
    - France, 1914 (Box 20, Folder 103)
    - France, Brooklyn (Connecticut), 1914-1915 (Box 20, Folder 104)
    - Puerto Rico, New York, 1915 (Box 20, Folder 105)
    - Brooklyn (Connecticut), New York, 1915-1918 (Box 20, Folder 106-109)
    - Brooklyn (Connecticut), 1918-1920 (Box 21, Folder 110-111)
    - Nice, 1920 (Box 21, Folder 112)
    - Nice, Brooklyn (Connecticut), 1920-1921 (Box 21, Folder 113)
    - Brooklyn (Connecticut), 1921-1922 (Box 21, Folder 114)
    - California, 1922 (Box 21, Folder 115-116)
    - California, Amherst (Massachusetts), 1922-1923 (Box 21, Folder 117)
    - France, 1923 (Box 21, Folder 118)
    - Brooklyn (Connecticut), New York, Washington, 1923-1924 (Box 22, Folder 119)
    - Fenwick (Connecticut), 1924-1925 (Box 22, Folder 120)
    - West Indies, 1925-1926 (Box 22, Folder 121-122)
    - Brooklyn (Connecticut), 1926-1927, undated (Box 22, Folder 123-125)
    - Bermuda, Undated (Box 22, Folder 126)
  - "A Little Book About the Two Children", 1889 (Box 22, Folder 127)
- Additional Material, 1841-1930, undated; Accession 2012-M-035
  - Commonplace Book, 1878-1896, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Bound volume containing a collection of newpaper clippings.
  - Consular material
    - Memoranda of subjects of correspondence, 1910 spring (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Notes
      - From the 1861-1905 dispatch books at Palermo, 1905 March (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - In preparation for the consular examination at Paris, 1903 January (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Miscellaneous, mainly connected with official duties as American Consul at Palermo and Genoa, 1891-1910, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Press comments on appointment as consul, 1902-1903, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence
    - A, 1899-1914, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Bickford, Marion, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Regarding Frances Walters Nelson.
      See also: Frances J. Walters, box 3, folder 4.
    - Bishop, William Henry
      - To Robert U. Johnson, 1892 October 3 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Miscellaneous, 1905-1910 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - B, 1888-1923, undated (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
    - C-G, 1877-1924, undated (Box 2, Folder 1-5)
    - Hope, Gertrude, 1917-1919 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - H-K, 1878-1926, undated (Box 2, Folder 7-10)
    - Lea, Henry C., 1906 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      Regarding documents concerning the trial of Francisco Lopez Diego by the Inquisition in Mexico, 1643-1646 (partial transcript included).
    - L, 1882-1912, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Marcellus family (mainly Irene, Virgilia, and Violette), 1916-1919 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - M-T, 1841-1926, undated (Box 2, Folder 14-20)
    - Valdés, A. Palacio, 1890-1930 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - "Various young women", 1915-1921 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Includes three locks of hair (donor unidentified).
    - V, 1882, 1903, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Walters, Frances J. (Mrs. Charles R. Nelson), 1917-1920 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      See also: Marion Bickford, box 1, folder 8.
    - W, Y-Z, 1898-1910, undated (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
    - Miscellaneous and undeciphered, 1887-1914, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Drawings and photographs, 1904, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Manuscripts, drafts, and notes
    The majority of these manuscripts are undated.
    - "Amos" (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Manuscript fragment, 7 pages.
    - "Armando Palacio Valdés" (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Preliminary notes and original manuscript of essay, circa 52 pages.
    - "Autumn Diversions of an Italian Country-House"
      - Original manuscript, 33 pages (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Photographs at Rivoli, Italy (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - "An Autumn Manoevre", 1878, 1900, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
      Preliminary notes, maps, and newspaper clippings.
    - "Back to Alma Mater", Circa 1923 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      Carbon copy of typewritten manuscript, with author's note: "For my class reunion at Yale, 1923".
    - "Benito Peréz Galdos" (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Preliminary notes and original manuscript, circa 67 pages.
    - "Cold Comfort for Manual Labor", 1877 September (Box 4, Folder 8)
      Manuscript copy of article published in Atlantic Monthly, 13 pages.
    - "Don Quixote" (Box 4, Folder 9)
      Notes for a play, 11 pages.
    - "Falardean's Cow", Circa 1873, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
      Printed copy with author's notes and revisions, 7 pages.
    - "The Great Circumgyratory Wedge: A Football Story" (Box 4, Folder 11)
      Marked by the author as "unuseable material", 53 pages.
    - "Jimmy Snow or the Exploits of the Good Knight 'Steveyhoe'", 1902, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
      Includes original manuscript of short story, notes, and clipping.
    - "The Jones' Servant Question" (Box 4, Folder 13)
      Original synopsis of play, 13 pages.
    - "Jose Maria de Pereda" (Box 4, Folder 14)
      Preliminary notes for proposed essay, circa 60 pages.
    - "Juan Valera" (Box 4, Folder 15)
      Notes and original manuscript of essay (24 pages) and original manuscript of translation from Valera (18 pages).
    - "Mr. Consul", 1899-1910, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
      Notes and letters for proposed book.
    - "On Foot from the Catskills" (Box 4, Folder 17)
      Original manuscript.
    - "Pathetic Ballad of a Shanty Boy", 1873 (Box 4, Folder 18)
      Printed pages with Bishop's handwritten notes explaining his authorship.
    - "Perez Galdos" (Box 4, Folder 19)
      Original manuscript of essay and translations of selections, 17 large folio pages.
    - "The Quadruple Alliance in Kewaydin" (Box 4, Folder 20)
      Preliminary notes, rough drafts, and incomplete manuscript version.
    - "The Rampant Lion, Hand, and Dagger"
      - Original manuscript of first version (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Original manuscript of revised version (Box 5, Folder 2)
        Read at the dinner of the Society of Colonial Wars.
    - "A Rich Girl: A Comedy of New York Manners and Customs", 1883, 1901, 1909, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
      Original typescript with author's handwritten corrections, miscellaneous notes and additions, clippings and leaflet.
    - "The Ships of Tarshish", 1889, 1896, 1912, undated (Box 5, Folder 4-5)
      Original manuscript with author's corrections, preliminary notes, notebook, correspondence, and clippings.
    - "Snorcum: A Vagary" (Box 5, Folder 6)
      Original illustrated manuscript.
    - "Some Travels Abroad", 1878-1904 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      Magazine and newspaper articles revised by the author for a proposed book.
    - "'Trader' Trafton" (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Typescript with author's heavy manuscript revisions and notes (11 pages), with additional miscellaneous notes (9 pages).
    - "Travels at Home", 1868-1925 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Magazine and newspaper articles annotated for proposed book.
    - "The Treasure Story", 1885 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Newspaper clippings.
    - "Their Worldly Goods" (Box 6, Folder 5)
      Typescript and carbon copy of short story with author's revisions, 34 pages each.
    - "A Villa at Rivoli" (Box 6, Folder 6)
      Original manuscript with illustrations.
    - "Wykeham's Daughters" (Box 6, Folder 7)
      A comedy founded on Goldoni's "Gli Inamorati" with notes, etc.
    - Random notes for a possible [?] Sicilian play (Box 6, Folder 8)